what I have been experiencing over the last five years
ما عشته خلال السنوات الخمس الماضية
in having the great privilege of traveling
حيث حظيت بفرصة السفر
to many of the poorest countries in the world.
إلى العديد من أفقر الدول في العالم.
This scene is one I see all the time everywhere,
ودائماً ما أرى هذا المشهد أينما ذهبت
and these young children are looking at a smartphone,
أولئك الأطفال على هواتفهم الذكية.
and the smartphone is having a huge impact in even the poorest countries.
تلك الهواتف لها تأثير كبير حتى في أفقر الدول.
I said to my team, you know,
قلت لفريقي: أتعلمون ما أرى
what I see is a rise in aspirations all over the world.
أرى زيادة في الطموح في كل بقاع الأرض.
In fact, it seems to me that there's a convergence of aspirations.
في الحقيقة يبدو لي أن مستوياته آخذت بالتقارب مع بعضها.
And I asked a team of economists to actually look into this.
فطلبت من فريق خبراء اقتصاديين البحث في ذلك
Is this true?
هل هو صحيح؟
Are aspirations converging all around the world?
هل تتقارب مستويات الطموح فعلاً حول العالم؟
So they looked at things like Gallup polls about satisfaction in life
فدرسوا استطلاعات الرأي المنجزة من طرف مؤسسة غالوب حول الرضا بالحياة
and what they learned was that if you have access to the internet,
ووجدوا أن إمكانية الولوج إلى تصفّح الانترنت
your satisfaction goes up.
تزيد من معدل الرضا بالحياة.
But another thing happens that's very important:
وتؤدي إلى شيء آخر، شيء مهمٌ جدّاً
your reference income,
وهو أن دخلكم المرجعي،
the income to which you compare your own,
أي ذلك الذي تستخدمونه لقياس مدى رضاكم عن دخلكم
also goes up.
يرتفع أيضاً.
Now, if the reference income of a nation, for example,
فمثلاً، إذا ارتفع الدخل المرجعي لمواطني دولة ما
goes up 10 percent
بنسبة 10٪
by comparing themselves to the outside,
عند مقارنة أنفسهم بمواطني دول أخرى،
then on average,
فيجب أن يرتفع
people's own incomes have to go up at least five percent
معدل دخل المواطن هناك بنسبة 5٪ على الأقل
to maintain the same level of satisfaction.
للمحافظة على معدل الرضا على الحياة.
But when you get down into the lower percentiles of income,
ولكن بالمقارنة مع المواطنين الأقلَّ دخلاً،
your income has to go up much more
فإن معدل دخلكم يجب أن يرتفع أكثر،
if the reference income goes up 10 percent,
إذا ازداد الدخل المرجعي بنسبة 10٪،
something like 20 percent.
لنسبة تقارب 20٪.
And so with this rise of aspirations,
ومع ارتفاع سقف الطموح،
the fundamental question is:
فإن السؤال الأساسي هو:
Are we going to have a situation
هل سنكون أمام مشكل
where aspirations are linked to opportunity
في الدول التي ترتبط فيها الطموحات بالفرص
and you get dynamism and economic growth,
وحيث النمو والحركية في الاقتصاد،
like that which happened in the country I was born in, in Korea?
كما حدث في مسقط رأسي كوريا؟
Or are aspirations going to meet frustration?
أم ستصطدم تلك الطموحات بالإحباط؟
This is a real concern, because between 2012 and 2015,
ذلك أمر مقلقٌ فعلاً، فبين عامي 2012 و2015،
terrorism incidents increased by 74 percent.
ارتفعت الأعمال الإرهابية بنسبة 74٪.
The number of deaths from terrorism went up 150 percent.
وعدد الوفيات بسبب الإرهاب بنسبة 150٪
Right now, two billion people
ويعيش الآن ملياري إنسان
live in conditions of fragility, conflict, violence,
في ظروف قاسية من الهشاشة والصراعات والعنف
and by 2030, more than 60 percent of the world's poor
وبحلول عام 2030 ستفوق نسبة الفقراء اللذين يعيشون
will live in these situations of fragility, conflict and violence.
في هشاشة وعنف وصراع 60%.
And so what do we do about meeting these aspirations?
فماذا سنفعل لتلبية تلك الطموحات؟
Are there new ways of thinking
هل هناك طرق تفكير جديدة
about how we can rise to meet these aspirations?
تمكننا من تلبية تلك الطموحات؟
Because if we don't, I'm extremely worried.
لأنه إن لم نتمكن من ذلك، فسأكون جد قلق.
Aspirations are rising as never before because of access to the internet.
لأن سقف الطموحات حول العالم في ارتفاع لم يسبق له مثيل بسبب الانترنت.
Everyone knows how everyone else lives.
كلنا على علم بمستوى معيشة الآخرين،
Has our ability to meet those aspirations
ولكن هل ازدادت قدرتنا على تلبية
risen as well?
تلك الطموحات؟
And just to get at the details of this,
ولنخوض في تفاصيل هذا الموضوع،
I want to share with you my own personal story.
أود أن أروي لكم قصتي.
This is not my mother,
هذه ليست أمي
but during the Korean War,
ولكن خلال الحرب بين الكوريّتين،
my mother literally took her own sister,
حملت أمّي أختها،
her younger sister, on her back,
أختها الصغرى، على ظهرها،
and walked at least part of the way
ومشت بها جزءاً من الطريق على الأقل
to escape Seoul during the Korean War.
لتتمكنا من الهرب من سيؤول خلال تلك الحرب.
Now, through a series of miracles,
ثم، خلال سلسلة من المعجزات
my mother and father both got scholarships to go to New York City.
حصل كِلا والديّ على منحة للدراسة في نيويورك.
They actually met in New York City and got married in New York City.
في الحقيقة، تقابل والديّ في مدينة نيويورك وتزوجا.
My father, too, was a refugee.
أبي كان لاجئا أيضاً.
At the age of 19, he left his family in the northern part of the country,
ترك عائلته في الجزء الشمالي من البلاد في سن التاسعة عشرة
escaped through the border
وعبر الحدود هارباً
and never saw his family again.
ولم يرى عائلته أبداً بعد ذلك.
Now, when they were married and living in New York,
حسناً، بعد أن تزوج والديّ وعاشا في نيويورك
my father was a waiter at Patricia Murphy's restaurant.
حيث عمل والدي كنادل في مطعم باتريشيا ميرفي.
Their aspirations went up.
زادت طموحاتهما.
They understood what it was like to live in a place like New York City
وأدركوا ما يعنيه العيش في مدينة مثل نيويورك
in the 1950s.
في الخمسينيات.
Well, my brother was born and they came back to Korea,
ثم عادوا إلى كوريا بعد ولادة شقيقي،
and we had what I remember as kind of an idyllic life,
وكما أذكر، تمتعنا بحياة مثالية.
but what was happening in Korea at that time
ولكن كوريا في ذلك الوقت
was the country was one of the poorest in the world
كانت من أفقر دول العالم
and there was political upheaval.
وكانت تعيش ثورة سياسية.
There were demonstrations just down the street from our house all the time,
دائماً ما كانت المظاهرات تندلع في حيّنا
students protesting against the military government.
طلّاب يتظاهرون ضد الحكومة العسكرية.
And at the time,
وفي ذلك الوقت،
the aspirations of the World Bank Group, the organization I lead now,
كانت توقعات مجموعة البنك الدولي، التي أترأسها الآن
were extremely low for Korea.
ضعيفة جدّاً لكوريا.
Their idea was that Korea would find it difficult without foreign aid
كانوا يعتقدون أنه في غياب الدعم الخارجي سيصعب على كوريا
to provide its people with more than the bare necessities of life.
تزويد مواطنيها بأكثر من احتياجات الحياة الأساسية.
So the situation is Korea is in a tough position,
فكانت كوريا تعيش موقفاً صعباً.
my parents have seen what life is like in the United States.
وكان والديّ قد تعرّفا إلى ماهية الحياة في الولايات المتحدة
They got married there. My brother was born there.
فقد تزوجا وأنجبا أخي فيها.
And they felt that in order to give us an opportunity
وخلصا إلى أن السبيل لتوفير الفرصة لنا
to reach their aspirations for us,
لتحقيق ما كانا يطمحانه لنا
we had to go and come back to the United States.
هو أن تعود عائلتنا إلى الولايات المتحدة.
Now, we came back.
فعدنا إلى الولايات المتحدة.
First we went to Dallas.
إلى دالاس في البداية،
My father did his dental degree all over again.
حيث أعاد والدي دراسته وحصل على شهادة طب الأسنان مرة أخرى
And then we ended up moving to Iowa, of all places.
ثم انتهى بنا المطاف في أيوا،
We grew up in Iowa.
وترعرعنا في أيوا.
And in Iowa, we went through the whole course.
وأكملت فيها كل مراحل دراستي
I went to high school, I went to college.
الثانوية والجامعية.
And then one day, something that I'll never forget,
وذات يوم حدث شيء لن أنساه أبداً
my father picked me up after my sophomore year in college,
عقب انتهاء سنتي الثانية في الجامعة، كان والدي
and he was driving me home,
يوصلني بسيارته إلى منزلنا،
and he said, "Jim, what are your aspirations?
وسألني قائلاً: "جيم، ما هو طموحك؟ "
What do you want to study? What do you want to do?"
ماذا تود أن تدرس؟ ما مجال العمل الذي تريده؟
And I said, "Dad," --
فقلت: "أبي"
My mother actually was a philosopher, and had filled us with ideas
كانت والدتي فيلسوفة زرعت فينا فكراً مشبعاً بالعدالة الاجتماعية
about protest and social justice,
عن التظاهر والاحتجاج
and I said, "Dad, I'm going to study political science and philosophy,
فقلت: "أبي، سأدرس الفلسفة والعلوم السياسية
and I'm going to become part of a political movement."
لأصبح جزءاً من الحركة السياسية."
My father, the Korean dentist,
فقام أبي، طبيب الأسنان الكوري
slowly pulled the car over to the side of the road --
بالتوقف على جانب الطريق ببطء...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He looked back at me, and he said,
ونظر إلي قائلاً:
"Jim, you finish your medical residency, you can study anything you want."
"جيم، حالما تنهي دراساتك الطبية، يمكنك دراسة ما تشاء"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I've told this story to a mostly Asian audience before.
حسناً، لقد رويت سابقاً هذه القصة لجمهور من أغلبية أسيوية
Nobody laughs. They just shake their head.
فلم يضحك أحد منهم، هزّوا رؤوسهم فقط
Of course.
طبعاً!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, tragically, my father died at a young age,
وكانت المأساة أن والدي توفي وهو ما يزال صغير السن
30 years ago at the age of 57,
منذ ثلاثين عاماً في السابعة والخمسين من العمر،
what happens to be how old I am right now,
وهو يصادف سنّي الآن
and when he died in the middle of my medical and graduate studies --
وعندما توفي أثناء دراستي للطب
You see, I actually got around it by doing medicine and anthropology.
في الواقع، لقد جمعت بين طلبه ورغبتي من خلال دراسة الطب وعلم الإنسان معا
I studied both of them in graduate school.
حيث درست كلا الاختصاصين ضمن دراساتي العليا
But then right about that time, I met these two people,
ثم في ذلك الوقت، تعرفت على هذين الشخصين
Ophelia Dahl and Paul Farmer.
أوفيليا داهل وبول فارمر
And Paul and I were in the same program.
حيث كنت وبول في نفس البرنامج
We were studying medicine
ندرس الطب معاً
and at the same time getting our PhD's in anthropology.
ونحضّر في الوقت ذاته لشهادة الدكتوراه في علم الإنسان.
And we began to ask some pretty fundamental questions.
وبدأنا نسأل أسئلة جوهرية
For people who have the great privilege of studying medicine and anthropology --
كنا من أولئك المحظوظين الذين سنحت لهم فرصة دراسة الطب وعلم الإنسان...
I had come from parents who were refugees.
مع أنني انحدرت من أبوين لاجئين.
Paul grew up literally in a bus in a swamp in Florida.
وبول تربّى في حافلة في مستنقع في فلوريدا
He liked to call himself "white trash."
حيث كان يحب أن يصف نفسه بالقمامة البيضاء
And so we had this opportunity
وسنحت لنا هذه الفرصة الثمينة
and we said,
فسألنا أنفسنا،
what is it that we need to do?
ما الذي علينا فعله الآن؟
Given our ridiculously elaborate educations,
مع تعليمنا المفصّل بشكل مضحك،
what is the nature of our responsibility to the world?
ما هي مسؤوليتنا تجاه العالم؟
And we decided that we needed to start an organization.
ووصلنا إلى قرار بتأسيس منظمة.
It's called Partners in Health.
أسميناها: "شركاء في الصحة"
And by the way, there's a movie made about that.
وبالمناسبة، تم إنتاج فيلم عن قصتنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There's a movie that was just a brilliant movie
فيلم رائع بحق
they made about it called "Bending the Arc."
أنتج حول المنظمة، اسمه "انحناء القوس"
It launched at Sundance this past January.
عرض في مهرجان "صن دانس" في يناير الماضي.
Jeff Skoll is here.
جيف سكول معنا اليوم،
Jeff is one of the ones who made it happen.
وهو أحد المساهمين في إنتاج الفيلم.
And we began to think about what it would take for us
وبدأنا نفكّر بما تتطلبه
to actually have our aspirations reach the level
تسوية مستويات طموحنا
of some of the poorest communities in the world.
بمستويات طموح المجتمعات الأكثر فقراً في العالم.
This is my very first visit to Haiti in 1988,
هذه أول زيارة لي لهايتي في 1988،
and in 1988, we elaborated a sort of mission statement,
وفي العام نفسه، حددنا ما يشبه بيان أهداف المنظمة،
which is we are going to make a preferential option for the poor
وهي أننا سنعتمد خيارا تفضيلياً للفقراء
in health.
في الصحة.
Now, it took us a long time, and we were graduate students in anthropology.
وتطلب ذلك منا وقتاً طويلاً، وكنا طلاب دراسات عليا في علم الإنسان.
We were reading up one side of Marx and down the other.
كنا نتدارس ماركس
Habermas. Fernand Braudel.
وهاريبماس وفيرناند برودل.
We were reading everything
درسنا كل ما يتعلق بالموضوع.
and we had to come to a conclusion of how are we going to structure our work?
وتحتم علينا أن نحدد منهجية عملنا.
So "O for the P," we called it,
فأطلقنا عليها اسم: "الخيار للفقراء"
a preferential option for the poor.
خيارً تفضيليً للفقراء
The most important thing about a preferential option for the poor
وأهمّ ما يتعلق بالخيار التفضيلي للفقراء،
is what it's not.
أنه ليس
It's not a preferential option for your own sense of heroism.
خياراً تفضيلياً لتعزيز شعورك بأنك بطل
for your own idea about how to lift the poor out of poverty.
لِما تؤمن بأنه انتشال الفقراء من فقرهم
It's not a preferential option for your own organization.
وليس خياراً تفضيلياً لمنظمتك،
And the hardest of all,
وأصعب من كل ذاك،
it's not a preferential option for your poor.
هو ليس خياراً تفضيلياً لفقرائك،
It's a preferential option for the poor.
إنه خيار تفضيليًّ لجميع الفقراء.
So what do you do?
فما الذي يمكنك فعله؟
Well, Haiti, we started building --
حسناً، بدأنا في هايتي ببناء...
Everyone told us, the cost-effective thing
أكّد لنا الجميع أنّ المجدي اقتصادياً
is just focus on vaccination and maybe a feeding program.
هو التركيز على التلقيح وربما تنظيم برنامج غذاء.
But what the Haitians wanted was a hospital.
ولكن ما أراده أهل هاييتي كان مشفى.
They wanted schools.
أرادوا مدارس.
They wanted to provide their children with the opportunities
أرادوا منح أولادهم الفرص
that they'd been hearing about from others, relatives, for example,
التي كانوا يسمعون بها من الآخرين. من أقربائهم، مثلاً،
who had gone to the United States.
الذين استقروا في الولايات المتحدة.
They wanted the same kinds of opportunities as my parents did.
أرادوا الفرص عينها التي أرادها والديّ لي.
I recognized them.
تفهمّت ذلك.
And so that's what we did. We built hospitals.
وهذا ما فعلناه. بنينا مستشفيات.
We provided education.
ووفرنا فرص التعليم.
And we did everything we could to try to give them opportunities.
وفعلنا ما بوسعنا لتوفير الفرص لهم.
Now, my experience really became intense
ولكن تجربتي تبلورت
at Partners in Health in this community, Carabayllo,
مع "شركاء في الصحة"، عندما كنا في هذا المنطقة: كارابايو
in the northern slums of Lima, Peru.
في أحياء مدينة ليما الشمالية الفقيرة في البيرو.
And in this community,
وفي هذه الأحياء،
we started out by really just going to people's homes and talking to people,
بدأنا أولاً بزيارة المنازل والتحدث مع الناس.
and we discovered an outbreak, an epidemic of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis.
واكتشفنا وجود وباء من السل المقاوم للأدوية.
This is Melquiades.
هذا ميلكيادس.
Melquiades was a patient at that time, he was about 18 years old,
كان ميلكيادس أحد المرضى في ذلك الوقت، وكان يبلغ الثامنة عشرة من العمر.
and he had a very difficult form of drug-resistant tuberculosis.
كان يعاني من حالة صعبة جدّاً من السل المقاوم للأدوية.
All of the gurus in the world, the global health gurus,
أكّد جميع خبراء العالم، خبراء الصحة على المستوى العالمي
said it is not cost-effective to treat drug-resistant tuberculosis.
أن علاج حالات السل المقاومة للأدوية، ليس مجدياً اقتصادياً.
It's too complicated. It's too expensive.
إنه معقد، وباهظ التكاليف.
You just can't do it. It can't be done.
لا يمكنك علاجه. لا يمكن لأحد علاجه.
And in addition, they were getting angry at us,
بل أنهم شعروا بالغضب تجاهنا.
because the implication was
لأن مضمون حديثهم كان
if it could be done, we would have done it.
لو كان ممكناً، لكنّا عالجناه نحن.
Who do you think you are?
من تظنون أنفسكم؟
And the people that we fought with were the World Health Organization
والذين تصارعنا معهم، كانوا منظمة الصحة العالمية
and probably the organization we fought with most
وكانت أكثر المنظمات صراعاً معنا
was the World Bank Group.
مجموعة البنك الدولي.
Now, we did everything we could
بذلنا قصار جهدنا
to convince Melquiades to take his medicines,
لإقناع ميلكيادس بتناول أدويته،
because it's really hard,
لأن ذلك صعب جدّاً،
and not once during the time of treatment did Melquiades's family ever say,
ولم يقل أي فرد من عائلته خلال فترة العلاج،
"Hey, you know, Melquiades is just not cost-effective.
"أتعلم، ميلكيادس ليس مجدياً اقتصادياً
Why don't you go on and treat somebody else?"
لم لا تعالج شخصاً آخر"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I hadn't seen Melquiades for about 10 years
ولم أر ميلكيادس بعد ذلك لعشر سنوات تقريباً
and when we had our annual meetings in Lima, Peru
وعندما عقدنا اجتماعاتنا السنوية في مدينة ليما في البيرو
a couple of years ago,
قبل سنتين،
the filmmakers found him
وجده صانعوا الفيلم
and here is us getting together.
وها نحن نجتمع معاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
He has become a bit of a media star because he goes to the film openings,
وغدا نجماً إعلامياً، لأنه يذهب إلى العروض الافتتاحية للفيلم،
and he knows how to work an audience now.
وتعلّم كيف يحفّز جمهوره الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But as soon as we won --
ولكن حالما كسبنا...
We did win. We won the argument.
فقد كسبنا فعلاُ، كسبنا الجدال.
You should treat multidrug-resistant tuberculosis --
يجب عليك علاج مرض السل المقاوم للأدوية
we heard the same arguments in the early 2000s about HIV.
واجهنا نفس الجدال في بداية الألفية الثانية حول مرض نقص المناعة المكتسبة
All of the leading global health people in the world said
أجمع خبراء الصحة العالمية حول العالم
it is impossible to treat HIV in poor countries.
أن من المستحيل علاج نقص المناعة المكتسبة في الدول الفقيرة.
Too expensive, too complicated, you can't do it.
إنه باهظ التكلفة وبالغ التعقيد، لا يمكنك علاجه.
Compared to drug-resistant TB treatment,
مقارنة مع علاج السل المقاوم للأدوية،
it's actually easier.
إنه في الواقع أسهل.
And we were seeing patients like this.
وكنا نرى مرضى
Joseph Jeune.
كجوزيف جون
Joseph Jeune also never mentioned that he was not cost-effective.
جوزيف جون أيضاً لم يذكر أبداً أنه ليس مجدٍ اقتصادياً
A few months of medicines, and this is what he looked like.
وبعد بضعة أشهر من العلاج، أصبح بهذا الشكل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We call that the Lazarus Effect of HIV treatment.
وهذا ما نطلق عليه اسم: تأثير لازاروس لعلاج الإيدز
Joseline came to us looking like this.
جوزلين أتت إلينا في هذه الحال
This is what she looked like a few months later.
وأصبحت هكذا بعد بضعة أشهر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, our argument, our battle, we thought,
ظننا أن جدالنا أو معركتنا
was with the organizations that kept saying it's not cost-effective.
كانت مع المنظمات التي تعنّتت في رأيها أن ذلك لم يكن مجدٍ اقتصادياً
We were saying, no,
ونحن رفضنا ذلك وأكّدنا
preferential option for the poor requires us to raise our aspirations
أنّ الخيار التفضيلي للفقراء يتطلب منّا أن نرفع سقف طموحاتنا
to meet those of the poor for themselves.
لمستوى طموحهم حول مستقبلهم.
And they said, well, that's a nice thought but it's just not cost-effective.
فقالوا حسناً هذا تفكير جيد، إلّا أنه ليس مجدياً اقتصادياً.
So in the nerdy way that we have operated Partners in Health,
فقمنا على طريقتنا المجتهدة المحبة للدراسة في "شركاء في الصحة"
we wrote a book against, basically, the World Bank.
بإصدار كتاب ننتقد فيه البنك الدولي نفسه
It says that because the World Bank
وكتبنا فيه أن تركيز البنك الدولي
has focused so much on just economic growth
بشكل كبير على النمو الاقتصادي فقط
and said that governments have to shrink their budgets
وحثّهم الحكومات على تقليص ميزانياتها
and reduce expenditures in health, education and social welfare --
وتخفيض مصاريف قطاعات الصحة والتعليم والرعاية الاجتماعية...
we thought that was fundamentally wrong.
كان خطأً جسيماً برأينا.
And we argued with the World Bank.
وتجادلنا مع البنك الدولي.
And then a crazy thing happened.
ثم حدث شيء غير متوقع.
President Obama nominated me to be President of the World Bank.
قام الرئيس باراك أوباما بترشيحي لرئاسة البنك الدولي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, when I went to do the vetting process with President Obama's team,
وعندما حضرت لبدء عملية التدقيق مع فريق الرئيس أوباما،
they had a copy of "Dying For Growth," and they had read every page.
كان الجميع قد قرؤوا كتابي "التفاني من أجل النمو" وأحضروا معهم نسخهم
And I said, "OK, that's it, right?
وقلت: "حسناً، هذه هي النهاية، صح؟
You guys are going to drop me?"
لن تقبلوا بترشيحي، أليس كذلك؟
He goes, "Oh, no, no, it's OK."
فردّ عليّ، "لا، لا عليك"
And I was nominated,
وتم ترشيحي،
and I walked through the door of the World Bank Group in July of 2012,
وعبرت أبواب مجموعة البنك الدولي في تموز من عام 2012،
and that statement on the wall, "Our dream is a world free of poverty."
وقرأت البيان المكتوب على الحائط، "حلمنا عالمٌ خالٍ من الفقر"
A few months after that, we actually turned it into a goal:
بعد بضعة أشهر، حولنا البيان إلى هدف:
end extreme poverty by 2030,
إنهاء الفقر المدقع بحلول عام 2030،
boost shared prosperity.
تعزيز الرخاء المشترك.
That's what we do now at the World Bank Group.
وهذا ما نقوم به الآن في مجموعة البنك الدولي.
I feel like I have brought the preferential option for the poor
وأشعر أنني أحضرت معي شعار الخيار التفضيلي للفقراء
to the World Bank Group.
إلى مجموعة البنك الدولي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But this is TED,
ولكننا الآن في TED
and so I want to share with you some concerns,
لذا أريد أن أخبركم ببعض الأمور المقلقة،
and then make a proposal.
ثم أريد أن أتقدم بعرض لكم.
The Fourth Industrial Revolution,
الثورة الصناعية الرابعة،
now, you guys know so much better than I do,
حسناً، أنتم أدرى بها منّي،
but here's the thing that concerns me.
ولكن ما يقلقني
What we hear about is job loss. You've all heard that.
أن جلّ ما نسمع عنه هو تقلص شواغر العمل،
Our own data suggest to us that two thirds of all jobs,
تشير بياناتنا أن ثلثي فرص العمل،
currently existing jobs in developing countries,
جميع فرص العمل الحالية في الدول النامية،
will be lost because of automation.
ستختفي بسبب الأتمتة
Now, you've got to make up for those jobs.
وعلينا أن نعوضها.
Now, one of the ways to make up for those jobs
أحد السبل للتعويض عن خسارة فرص العمل
is to turn community health workers into a formal labor force.
هي جعل العاملين في الخدمات الطبية المجتمعية جزء من القوة العاملة
That's what we want to do.
ذلك ما نسعى إليه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We think the numbers will work out,
نعتقد أن ذلك سيحقق توازناً،
that as health outcomes get better and as people have formal work,
ونعتقد أن تحسّن نتائج قطاع الصحة وحصول العاملين على عمل رسمي
we're going to be able to train them
سيمكننا من تدريبهم
with the soft-skills training that you add to it
على المهارات السلوكية المهنية الأخرى
to become workers that will have a huge impact,
التي ستجعل منهم قوة عاملة مؤثرّة.
and that may be the one area that grows the most.
يمكن أن يغدو هذا المجال الأكثر نموّاً.
But here's the other thing that bothers me:
ولكن هناك أمراً أخر يقلقني:
right now it seems pretty clear to me that the jobs of the future
من الواضح لي الآن أن فرص العمل في المستقبل
will be more digitally demanding,
ستتطلب مهارات تقنية عالية،
and there is a crisis in childhood stunting.
ولكننا نواجه أزمة هي قصور تطور الدماغ عند الأطفال
So these are photos from Charles Nelson, who shared these with us
بالنظر إلى هذه الصور التي أرسلها لنا تشارلز نيلسون
from Harvard Medical School.
من كلية الطب في جامعة هارفرد
And what these photos show on the one side, on the left side,
وتظهر الصورة في الجانب الأيسر
is a three-month-old who has been stunted:
دماغ طفل مصاب بقصور نمو الدماغ
not adequate nutrition, not adequate stimulation.
لم يتلق الغذاء الكافي، وبالتالي التحفيز المناسب.
And on the other side, of course, is a normal child,
وفي الجانب الآخر، طبعاً دماغ طفل طبيعي
and the normal child has all of these neuronal connections.
تفعلت فيه اتصالات الخلايا العصبية بشكل كامل.
Now, the neuronal connections are important,
وللعلم، إن اتصالات الخلايا العصبية مهمة،
because that is the definition of human capital.
لأنها أساس ما ندعوه رأس المال البشري.
Now, we know that we can reduce these rates.
نحن متأكدون أننا نستطيع تقليص تلك النسب
We can reduce these rates of childhood stunting quickly,
نسب الإصابة بقصور نمو الدماغ بسرعة
but if we don't, India, for example, with 38 percent childhood stunting,
ولكن إذا لم نفعل، فكيف ستنافس الهند مثلاً في اقتصاد المستقبل
how are they going to compete in the economy of the future
بنسبة تفوق 38% من قصور نمو الدماغ لدى أطفالها،
if 40 percent of their future workers cannot achieve educationally
إذا كان 40% من قوتها العاملة غير قادرة على التحصيل الدراسي
and certainly we worry about achieving economically
وطبعاً نحن نخشى على النجاح اقتصاديا
in a way that will help the country as a whole grow.
بشكل يعزز نمو البلد بأكمله.
Now, what are we going to do?
فما الذي سنفعله الآن؟
78 trillion dollars is the size of the global economy.
حجم الاقتصاد العالمي 78 تريليون دولار.
8.55 trillion dollars are sitting in negative interest rate bonds.
منها 8,55 تريليون دولار على شكل سندات مالية ذات فائدة سلبية.
That means that you give the German central bank your money
ويعني ذلك أنك تعطي أموالك للبنك المركزي الألماني
and then you pay them to keep your money.
ثم تدفع فوائد لهم ليحتفظوا بها لك.
That's a negative interest rate bond.
تلك هي السندات المالية بالفائدة السلبية
24.4 trillion dollars in very low-earning government bonds.
و24,4 تريليون دولار في سندات مالية حكومية ضئيلة الأرباح.
And 8 trillion literally sitting in the hands of rich people
و8 تريليون دولار في أيدي أغنياء العالم
under their very large mattresses.
يكنزونها تحت أسرّتهم الضخمة.
What we are trying to do is now use our own tools --
ما نحاول فعله الآن هو استخدام أدواتنا
and just to get nerdy for a second,
لنتحول للحظة إلى ذوي أدمغة،
we're talking about first-loss risk debt instruments,
نتحدث هنا عن أدوات لتحديد مخاطر الديون،
we're talking about derisking, blended finance,
نتحدث عن تحييد المخاطرة، والتمويل المتعدد
we're talking about political risk insurance,
نتحدث عن التأمين ضد المخاطر السياسية،
credit enhancement --
تحسين الديون...
all these things that I've now learned at the World Bank Group
تعلمت كل تلك الأدوات من خلال عملي في مجموعة البنك الدولي
that rich people use every single day to make themselves richer,
وأغنياء العالم يستخدمون تلك الأدوات كل يوم لزيادة ثرواتهم.
but we haven't used aggressively enough on behalf of the poor
بينما لم نستخدم تلك الأدوات بالشكل الكافي بالنيابة عن الفقراء
to bring this capital in.
لتأسيس رأس مال لهم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So does this work?
فهل يجدي ذلك نفعاً؟
Can you actually bring private-sector players into a country
هل بإمكاننا إحضار لاعبين من القطاع الخاص إلى بلد ما
and really make things work?
وإحراز النجاح؟
Well, we've done it a couple of times.
حسناً، لقد قمنا بذلك عدة مرات.
This is Zambia, Scaling Solar.
هذا مشروع سكالينغ سولار في زامبيا.
It's a box-set solution from the World Bank
نوفر لكم مجموعة حلول متكاملة من البنك الدولي
where we come in and we do all the things you need
حيث نأتي ونقوم بكل ما يلزمك
to attract private-sector investors.
لاستقدام مستثمري القطاع الخاص.
And in this case, Zambia went from having a cost of electricity
في هذا المثال، خفّضت زامبيا كلفة الكهرباء
at 25 cents a kilowatt-hour,
بـ 25 سنتاً للكيلوواط في الساعة،
and by just doing simple things, doing the auction,
وذلك بأمور بسيطة، مثل المزاد العلني،
changing some policies,
وتغيير بعض السياسات،
we were able to bring the cost down.
استطعنا تخفيض الكلفة.
Lowest bid,
أقل العروض كلفة،
25 cents a kilowatt-hour for Zambia?
25 سنتاً للكيلوواط في الساعة لزامبيا؟
The lowest bid was 4.7 cents a kilowatt-hour. It's possible.
أخفض العروض كانت 4,7 سنتاً للكيلوواط في الساعة. إنه ممكن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But here's my proposal for you.
وهذا هو عرضي لكم.
This is from a group called Zipline,
من مجموعة اسمها زيبلاين،
a cool company, and they literally are rocket scientists.
شركة رائعة من علماء الصواريخ. توصلوا لطريقة
They figured out how to use drones in Rwanda.
تمكنهم من تحليق طائرات بلا طيار في روندا.
This is me launching a drone in Rwanda
وهذه صورتي وأنا أطلق إحداها في روندا
that delivers blood anywhere in the country
يمكنها توصيل الدم إلى أي مكان في الدولة
in less than an hour.
في أقل من ساعة.
So we save lives,
فننقذ الأرواح،
this program saved lives --
هذا البرنامج، ينقذ الأرواح...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This program made money for Zipline
هذا البرنامج جنى المال للشركة
and this program saved huge amounts of money for Rwanda.
ووفر في الوقت ذاته أموالا طائلة على روندا.
That's what we need, and we need that from all of you.
وهذا ما نريده، ونريده منكم جميعاً.
I'm asking you, carve out a little bit of time in your brains
أسألكم أن تعطوا بعض الوقت
to think about the technology that you work on,
للتفكير في التكنولوجيا التي تطورونها،
the companies that you start, the design that you do.
والشركات التي تؤسسونها، والتصاميم التي تنتجونها.
Think a little bit and work with us
فكّروا قليلاً وتعاونوا معنا
to see if we can come up with these kinds of extraordinary win-win solutions.
فلربما نتكمن من ابتكار مثل هذه الحلول المفيدة لنا جميعاً.
I'm going to leave you with one final story.
وسأختم حديثي بهذه القصة.
I was in Tanzania, and I was in a classroom.
كنت في تانزانيا، في فصل دراسي.
This is me with a classroom of 11-year-olds.
هذا أنا في فصل مع طلاب في 11 من العمر.
And I asked them, as I always do,
وسألتهم، كالعادة،
"What do you want to be when you grow up?"
"ماذا تريدون أن تصبحوا عندما تكبرون؟"
Two raised their hands and said,
رفع اثنان أيدهما وقالا:
"I want to be President of the World Bank."
"أريد أن أصبح رئيس البنك الدولي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And just like you, my own team and their teachers laughed.
وكما ضحكتم الآن، ضحك أفراد فريقي والمدرسين كذلك.
But then I stopped them.
ولكنني أوقفتهم عندها.
I said, "Look, I want to tell you a story.
وقلت لهم: "أريد أن أروي لكم قصة.
When I was born in South Korea, this is what it looked like.
عندما ولدت في كوريا الجنوبية، كانت بلدي في هذه الحالة.
This is where I came from.
هذا مسقط رأسي.
And when I was three years old,
وعندما كنت في الثالثة من العمر،
in preschool,
في الحضانة،
I don't think that George David Woods, the President of the World Bank,
لا أعتقد أن لو زار رئيس البنك الدولي حينها، جورج دايفد ودز
if he had visited Korea on that day and come to my classroom,
كوريا في ذلك اليوم وحضر إلى صفّي،
that he would have thought
ليتصور
that the future President of the World Bank
أن الرئيس المستقبلي للبنك الدولي
was sitting in that classroom.
كان ضمن طلاب ذلك الصف.
Don't let anyone ever tell you
لا تسمحوا لأحد أبداً أن يقول لكم
that you cannot be President of the World Bank."
أن ليس باستطاعتكم ترأس البنك الدولي"
Now -- thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Let me leave you with one thought.
وسأترككم مع هذه الفكرة.
I came from a country that was the poorest in the world.
أنا أنحدر من بلد كان من أفقر دول العالم.
I'm President of the World Bank.
وأنا الآن رئيس البنك الدولي.
I cannot and I will not pull up the ladder behind me.
لن أكون حجر عثرة أمام القادمين من بعدي.
This is urgent.
هذا أمر عاجلٌ.
Aspirations are going up.
الطموح في ازدياد.
Everywhere aspirations are going up.
إنه في ازدياد في كلِّ مكان.
You folks in this room, work with us.
أطلب منكم أيها الحضور أن تتعاونوا معنا.
We know that we can find those Zipline-type solutions
نحن متأكدون أننا نستطيع ابتكار حلول كزيبلاين
and help the poor leapfrog into a better world,
وأننا نستطيع مساعدة الفقراء على التطور إلى عالم أفضل.
but it won't happen until we work together.
ولكن ذلك لن يحدث، حتّى نتعاون معاً.
The future "you" -- and especially for your children --
"أنت" المستقبلي... وخاصة لأطفالك...
the future you
أنت المستقبلي
will depend on how much care and compassion we bring
سيعتمد على مدى اهتمامنا ورعايتنا اليوم
to ensuring that the future "us" provides equality of opportunity
لنتأكد أن "نحن" المستقبليين سنوفر فرصاً عادلة
for every child in the world.
لكل طفل في العالم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
شكراً، شكراً، شكراً
Chris Anderson: You'd almost think
كريس أندرسون: قد يبدو لك
people are surprised to hear a talk like this
أن الحضور اعترتهم الدهشة لسماع خطاب كهذا
from the President of the World Bank.
من رئيس البنك الدولي.
It's kind of cool.
من الرائع رؤية ذلك.
I'd encourage you to even be a little more specific on your proposal.
أود الطلب منك أن تخوض أكثر بتفاصيل عرضك.
There's many investors, entrepreneurs in this room.
فهناك العديد من المستثمرين ورواد الأعمال في الحضور.
How will you partner with them? What's your proposal?
وضح لهم رجاء كيف ستتشارك معهم. ما هو عرضك لهم؟
Jim Yong Kim: Can I get nerdy for just a second.
جيم يونغ كيم: أتسمح لي بتحدث لغة الأرقام للحظة؟
CA: Get nerdy. Absolutely. JYK: So here's what we did.
كريس: بالتأكيد! جيم: هذا ما أنجزناه.
Insurance companies never invest in developing country infrastructure,
شركات التأمين لا تستثمر أبداً في مشاريع البنية التحتية للدول النامية،
for example, because they can't take the risk.
مثلاً، لأنهم لا يستطيعون تحمل المخاطرة.
They're holding money for people who pay for insurance.
لأنهم يحتفظون بالمال لأولئك الذين يشترون خدمات التأمين.
So what we did was a Swedish International Development Association
الذي قمنا به هو أن جمعية سويدش انترناشيونال للتطوير
gave us a little bit of money,
قدمت لنا مبلغاً من المال،
we went out and raised a little bit more money, a hundred million,
وقمنا بجمع المزيد من المال، مائة مليون دولار
and we took first loss, meaning if this thing goes bad,
وقمنا بتحمل الخسارة الأولى، ففي حال فشل المشروع
10 percent of the loss we'll just eat,
سنتحمل نحن 10% من الخسارة،
and the rest of you will be safe.
وسيكونون بأمان.
And that created a 90-percent chunk, tranche
وبذلك بقي لدينا هامش من 90%
that was triple B, investment-grade, so the insurance companies invested.
من الاستثمار من درجة BBB، فقامت شركات التأمين بالاستثمار.
So for us, what we're doing is taking our public money
وبالنسبة لنا، فنحن نستخدم أموالنا العامة
and using it to derisk specific instruments
لتخفيض مخاطر الاستثمار في أدوات معينة
to bring people in from the outside.
لجذب الناس من الخارج.
So all of you who are sitting on trillions of dollars of cash,
فانضموا إلينا يا أصحاب التريليونات من الأموال،
come to us. Right?
انضموا إلينا، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: And what you're specifically looking for are investment proposals
كريس: ما تبحث عنه بالتحديد هي عروض استثمار
that create employment in the developing world.
توفر فرص عمل في الدول النامية.
JYK: Absolutely. Absolutely.
جيم: تماما، تماما
So these will be, for example, in infrastructure that brings energy,
من الممكن أن تكون في مجال البنية التحتية لإنتاج الطاقة،
builds roads, bridges, ports.
أو بناء الطرق، أو الجسور، أو الموانئ.
These kinds of things are necessary to create jobs,
تلك المجالات أساسية لخلق فرص العمل،
but also what we're saying is
ولكننا ما نود قوله هو
you may think that the technology you're working on
أنه من الممكن أن تظنوا أن التكنولوجيا التي تطورونها
or the business that you're working on
أو الأعمال التي تطورونها
may not have applications in the developing world,
لا يمكن الاستفادة منها في الدول النامية،
but look at Zipline.
ولكن انظروا إلى زيبلاين.
And that Zipline thing didn't happen
لم ينجح التعاون مع زيبلاين
just because of the quality of the technology.
بسبب جودة التكنولوجيا.
It was because they engaged with the Rwandans early
بل بسبب حوارهم مع الروانديين مبكراً
and used artificial intelligence --
واستخدامهم الذكاء الاصطناعي...
one thing, Rwanda has great broadband --
إن شبكة الاتصالات في روندا جيدة...
but these things fly completely on their own.
ولكن هذه الطائرات تطير بلا أية مساعدة.
So we will help you do that. We will make the introductions.
سنساعدكم على تنفيذ مشاريع مشابهة، سنعرّفكم بالأشخاص المعنيين.
We will even provide financing. We will help you do that.
بل سنزودكم بالدعم المالي أيضاً، لتنجحوا.
CA: How much capital is the World Bank willing to deploy
كريس: ما هو حجم الدعم المالي الذي يمكن أن تقدموه
to back those kinds of efforts?
لدعم مثل تلك المبادرات؟
JYK: Chris, you're always getting me to try to do something like this.
جيم: كريس، أنت دائماً ما تضعني في هذا الموقف.
CA: I'm trying to get you in trouble. JYK: So here's what we're going to do.
كريس: أنا أحاول توريطك الآن جيم: حسناً، هذه خطتنا:
We have 25 billion a year that we're investing in poor countries,
نستثمر سنوياً 25 مليار دولار في الدول الفقيرة،
the poorest countries.
الدول الأفقر في العالم.
And as we invest over the next three years,
وعندما نستثمر خلال السنوات الثلاث المقبلة،
25 billion a year,
25 مليار دولار سنويّاً،
we have got to think with you
علينا أن نفكّر معكم
about how to use that money more effectively.
بأكثر الطرق فعاليّة لاستخدام تلك الأموال.
So I can't give you a specific number. It depends on the quality of the ideas.
لا يمكنني إعطائكم رقماً محدداً، ذلك يعتمد على جودة الأفكار.
So bring us your ideas,
فشاركونا بأفكاركم،
and I don't think that financing is going to be the problem.
ولا أظن أن تمويلها سيشكل مشكلة.
CA: All right, you heard it from the man himself.
كريس: حسناً، لقد سمعتموه جميعاً.
Jim, thanks so much. JYK: Thank you. Thank you.
جيم، شكراً جزيلاً. جيم: شكراً، شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)